Victoria Wood: Hi, Jiangkun. How are you?
Victoria Wood: Hello, hello!
Monica Daley (she, her): Hi, everyone!
Victoria Wood: How are you doing, Monica?
Monica Daley (she, her): Juno.
Monica Daley (she, her): For the kids, so it's a busy week.
Monica Daley (she, her): Settling back into the early morning routine.
Victoria Wood: Nice. When does school start for them?
Monica Daley (she, her): For my older kids, 7am.
Victoria Wood: Oh.
Monica Daley (she, her): Yeah.
Monica Daley (she, her): So he has to leave the house, he rides his bike, and he has to leave the house at 6.30.
Victoria Wood: Oh, man.
Monica Daley (she, her): Which is very early for me.
Victoria Wood: I don't know, at high school, I feel like just…
Victoria Wood: I haven't had to wake up that early since I was a teenager.
Monica Daley (she, her): It doesn't make any sense, because teenagers' brains are wired to be, like, you know, night owls, and so it doesn't, you know, they really should be allowed to sleep in.
Victoria Wood: Yeah.
Victoria Wood: Hi, Simon.
Simon N Sponberg: I was muted, sorry.
Simon N Sponberg: Okay.
Victoria Wood: I guess we can give people another minute or so to join in.
Victoria Wood: And then I just wanted to do a couple quick announcements, and then I'll hand it over to you to introduce yourselves, and then…
Victoria Wood: Get started.
Victoria Wood: You know, a lot of our teams are actually done at this point, so…
Victoria Wood: It's nice to see that we still have a good turnout today.
Victoria Wood: All right. Okay, so a few quick announcements. First of all, welcome everybody. And second of all,
Victoria Wood: I, in this last week, I sent out, the, application for conference travel funding. If you have any questions about that, let me know.
Victoria Wood: The… the big thing to know is, that one of the big conferences that most of our trainees do tend to make use of is, the Society for Integrative and Comparative Biology, which is gonna be in January in Pittsburgh this year. And the abstracts for submitting to that are due on August 28th, so that's in the next week or so.
Victoria Wood: So make sure that you're discussing with your team and writing up an abstract if that's something you all want to do.
Victoria Wood: And then let me know if you have any questions about eligibility requirements or anything like that for the funding application.
Victoria Wood: And then the other quick thing is, Capstone Symposium schedule is all set, so you should know when your, when your, presentation is, and, I'll be sending out the final version of that, just a prettier version of what you guys have already seen in the next few days, so you guys can have a PDF version of that on hand.
Victoria Wood: But, make sure that if you're coming in person, you have RSVP'd and, are already booking travel and housing and such. You should do that soon if you haven't done so already.
Victoria Wood: That's all I've got. So I'll hand it over to our team presenting today.
Simon N Sponberg: Okay, great. So, I will start us off. My name is Simon Sponberg. I'm going to share my slides, and I'll introduce the other folks in just a second.
Simon N Sponberg: Oops, wrong one.
Simon N Sponberg: I'm sure… Wrong share.
Simon N Sponberg: This slide… alright, here we go.
Simon N Sponberg: Here we go!
Simon N Sponberg: Okay, so, this is going to be the muscle X-ray diffraction, workshop, and we're going to talk about a, really cool technique
Simon N Sponberg: that allows us to get, certain kinds of information that are really typically unavailable from a lot of other methods. And so we wanted to give an introduction to that today. My name's Simon Sponberg, I'm a professor here at Georgia Tech. I will be doing a short introduction, and what I'm going to do is, instead of really introducing the technique, I'm going to start you with an example of how it was used in a study that we did.
Simon N Sponberg: So that you can have a reference for what we can do biologically with this kind of thing, because I think that's very important to sort of ground it. And then, the important people are going to come up, and the first rule of presentations is don't use over-exaggerated animations, but in this case, it's really, really, really important, because they're the really important people. So this is John Kun and Casey. Dr. Jiangkun Wei is a postdoc with us here at Georgia Tech.
Simon N Sponberg: And he is also the formal X-ray diffraction specialist
Simon N Sponberg: for the MZ network. I don't know if he even knows that it's his formal
Simon N Sponberg: role, but he is our champion X-ray diffraction guy. He's only been with us for less than a year and has already done a lot of cool stuff, but he's going to take you through the method in a lot more detail after I give you the introduction. And then Casey is going to actually take you through a little bit of an online, real-time example of how you sort of look at this data and analyze it. Okay, so we're hoping that by the end of this, you really have an understanding
Simon N Sponberg: What the technique is, how you would use it, why you would use it, and a few examples of what you could use it for.
Simon N Sponberg: All right, here's your sign-in. We'll bring this up again at the end of the, workshop, if people want to grab that really fast.
Simon N Sponberg: And then I'm going to go on.
Simon N Sponberg: And if you don't have any idea what X-ray diffraction is, and you're not sure what I was even just mentioning, great, we're just about to talk about it.
Simon N Sponberg: It's a very exciting thing, I think, for some things, but it also has a lot of limitations. All right.
Simon N Sponberg: Now that people have had that, let's do the introduction. Okay, you all have had a lot of workshops at this point in time. I don't need to tell you that muscle is special, and muscle is special in very particular ways, but one of the ways that it's really, really important is that it's fairly unique as a tissue.
Simon N Sponberg: Because it's so hierarchical.
Simon N Sponberg: And so well organized. And it has certain kinds of things that are widely conserved across species. And one of those is the sort of fundamental structure of skeletal muscle, at least, although it's true for cardiac, too, that it's organized into these hierarchical scale… length scales that are typically organized around this sarcomere.
Simon N Sponberg: And one of the cool things about sarcomeres is sarcomeres is regardless of whether you're a human, a cockroach, or a blue whale, they tend to all be roughly the same length, especially if you're a vertebrate.
Simon N Sponberg: If you're a vertebrate, your sarcomeres vary by very little, usually no more than 1 to 10 microns.
Simon N Sponberg: And, that even extends to most invertebrates. And so that's pretty remarkable. You can have many, many ranges of size, but you have this almost what we would call in physics, an invariant length scale that is, present throughout those. And it sort of tells you that there's a lot of conserved organization of muscle.
Simon N Sponberg: So even if you get a really big muscle, at this level, you're going to get a lot of conservation of the fundamental structure. And many of you know already, or should remember, that that's because of the structure of the molecular filaments and proteins that are enabling muscle to contract. This interdigitation of thick filaments and thin filaments, where the thick filaments contain the myosin that have the little active heads.
Simon N Sponberg: illustrated here on the bottom right, and the thin filaments have the binding sites for those. And again, we're just, as a reminder, we call when a bias and head binds to an actin-containing thin filament, we call that a cross bridge.
Simon N Sponberg: Okay, so there's been some discussion about this. This molecular scale is really essential, though, because it's at this scale that it's oftentimes really hard to get good information.
Simon N Sponberg: And that's what we're going to address a little bit today, and it's especially hard to get good information dynamically. What that means is when you want to make a video. And so you… many of you have probably seen a video like this online of a myosin head binding forming a cross bridge and sliding an actin filament along. And these videos are great for visualization.
Simon N Sponberg: But you better be pretty dang critical of these videos. There's a lot of things that this misses. First of all, like, ATP just sort of floats in from the ether there. There's nothing else
Simon N Sponberg: drawn in this picture, and the length scale here is about 20 nanometers, okay?
Simon N Sponberg: A nanometer is the size of a water molecule between an angstrom and a nanometer, so there's, like, a very finite amount of space here, and even the individual component clutter of other ions in this space are going to make it very, very crowded.
Simon N Sponberg: So, there's a lot of things that these animations miss, and there's a lot of assumptions that they make.
Simon N Sponberg: So, for example, if you watch the video again, the actin filament slides left and right. And in fact, if we think about the sliding filament theory, that's what we've talked about for a long time, is that we always sort of draw it as these thick filaments and these thin filaments sliding across each other.
Simon N Sponberg: But I just got done telling you that muscle is really structured hierarchically and within a lot of organization. And really, actually, muscle makes this 3D pattern, and this is going to become really important. So, here's a fundamental question that that animation didn't even get at yet.
Simon N Sponberg: If you slide this way, Horizontally. What happens, in this case, vertically?
Simon N Sponberg: Right?
Simon N Sponberg: So most things, when you push them, they expand, right? If they're isovolumetric, they expand. And so that actually goes back to a really, really important study that was done a long, long time ago by this guy, Jan Swammerdam.
Simon N Sponberg: In 1666, he was a really good experimentalist, and he was a big devotee of Descartes, the guy who came up with Cartesian coordinates, right?
Simon N Sponberg: And Descartes had this idea of vital energies, that what happens when a muscle contracts is that there's this vital energy taken from the ether that is pumped through the nerves, and it swells the muscle up.
Simon N Sponberg: Right? And so Swamadam wanted to test this. He wanted to measure the volume of this spirit energy, of this ether. And so what he knew… what he did is he took a frog muscle, he put it inside a chamber here on the right, and he put… filled it with fluid, and he put a little float at the top, and they… and then he took the nerve, and he stretched it out inside of the chamber. And they knew that if you tweaked the nerve, and the muscle was fresh, you could get the muscle to contract.
Simon N Sponberg: And so his idea here is that he would pinch the nerve, and the muscle would contract, and the float would go up, and the amount that the float goes up tells you how much of the volume of that spirit energy is.
Simon N Sponberg: And of course, he did this experiment, and the float didn't move, because muscles are isovolumetric, at least at the cell scale.
Simon N Sponberg: And this was actually really problematic for Swammerdam, because he wrote in his journal that, you know, there must be something wrong with my experiment, because there's no way Desart is wrong, which is a good lesson, never trust your advisors. In fact, that's the first rule of my lab. And in fact, it has sort of a sad story, because, like, after this experiment, Jan Swamderdam joined an end-of-days cult.
Simon N Sponberg: Where he eventually died. So, like, he actually left science because of this. So trust your data, not your advisor.
Simon N Sponberg: But please do listen to your advisor. Okay. Muscle is isovolumetric at the cell scale.
Simon N Sponberg: But what about at that myofilament lettuce scale? What about at the sarcomere level? What happens if you shorten a muscle.
Simon N Sponberg: Does the lattice expand?
Simon N Sponberg: Or does it shrink?
Simon N Sponberg: And this is really important, because if you think about what's happening there, you've got a myosin head interacting with actin. There's a binding site on actin. When you have two molecules interacting, you can draw, like, a free energy diagram. This is just sort of a cartoon version of it, but it is sort of this shape. And so, like, the further this actin filament is away from the myosin.
Simon N Sponberg: The less likely it's going to be to bind, or the more likely it's going to be to bind, depending on where it is.
Simon N Sponberg: In that space. So if the lattice is moving, it's going to affect the binding probability, and in fact, we know that there's significant forces produced by the myosin heads, as well as in the axial direction, as well as in the radial direction, as well as in the axial direction.
Simon N Sponberg: So, what is the role of this radial change in lattice spacing?
Simon N Sponberg: for the function of a muscle. And how the heck would you measure this? Because it's at the time… at the length scale of tens of nanometers.
Simon N Sponberg: And tens of nanometers is shorter than the wavelength of visible light, so you're pretty much screwed if you want to try and measure it with a light microscope.
Simon N Sponberg: Right? You can use an electron microscope, but then you have to freeze the muscle, fracture it, and measure it statically. So what if you want to do it dynamically? Well, you can do what any sane person does, which is you take your muscle and you bring it to a particle accelerator.
Simon N Sponberg: This is the advanced photon source at Argonne National Lab, and the MZ collaborative team includes Tom Irving and his team there, Wei Kong Ma, at the BioCat X-ray beamline. And so what, if you haven't seen a particle accelerator before, there's a linear accelerator that spins up a bunch of electrons, and then you strip off photons from that, and the photons are extremely high energy, they're X-rays.
Simon N Sponberg: But you'll get x-rays on the dental office. It's not so hard to create x-rays. What's really impressive about these particle accelerators is the amount of photons they can produce. They can create a really, really bright x-ray beam, and then you can focus it down, and you can shoot it through muscle. And when you shoot it through living muscle.
Simon N Sponberg: you see something really interesting. You see a pattern like this, and this is what we're going to talk about today. This is a diffraction pattern.
Simon N Sponberg: And Jiangkun will introduce what a diffraction pattern is and why it happens. But for now, what it is, is it's going to correspond to the spacing differences between the thick filaments and the thin filaments. So if you look at one of those sarcomeres in cross-section, the red thick filaments and the blue thin filaments are organized in this regular lattice. Well, a lattice is a crystal.
Simon N Sponberg: And when you shoot energy light through a crystal at the right wavelength, it will diffract, it will create these little spots, and those spots will help correspond to the spacings that you see in that lattice. So if we want to tell if the muscle is changing the distance between actin and myosin, we can use this X-ray diffraction technique. There's a lot of other things it can tell you, and Jiangkun will talk about that.
Simon N Sponberg: shortly. But I want to give you one example of how we use this, and it was to resolve… there's other diffraction peaks I'll also talk about.
Simon N Sponberg: We can also do this with really high time resolution with modern X-ray detectors, because we have so many photons going through. Here is it shooting through a flight muscle and a moth, but you can get samples down to the level of a millisecond. So you can potentially image the diffraction pattern and get information about the contraction of muscles, and this is at the molecular scale. And so here is a much dimmer image, so you only see three spots of that diffraction pattern.
Simon N Sponberg: But this is actually a cockroach muscle in the beam that's contracting in about 40 milliseconds. It's slowed down, and we're watching the change in those dots. The rotation is just because of a change in the angle of the muscle.
Simon N Sponberg: But the change in the spot's intensity and their spacing, if you look carefully, will help correspond to the change in the spacing of the myofilament lattice with inside muscle.
Simon N Sponberg: All right. So, can these microscopic lattice spacing properties, nanoscale properties, affect the macroscopic properties of muscle as a whole tissue? That's the first thing you'd want to know, right, for us in IMSI. And so, let me start you off with everybody's favorite animal, a cockroach.
Simon N Sponberg: I'm sorry, I should have given a trigger warning before that ran across the screen. The cockroach is very interesting, you've probably heard a few different examples of this before, because it's been very well studied, a couple of its muscles, and a cockroach has a mystery embedded in its leg.
Simon N Sponberg: And this mystery was explored by Travis, too. It was first identified in Anna Ann's classic papers from 2000, which I really encourage everybody to read if they're part of MZ. But Travis wanted to figure out this mystery, and here's the mystery. There are two muscles, there are many muscles in the leg of the cockroach, but there's two of them. Muscle 178, 179, don't worry about the numbers.
Simon N Sponberg: The red muscle and the blue muscle is fun. These two muscles are really interesting, because they act on the same joint.
Simon N Sponberg: They have the exact same neural activation, the same single motor neuron goes to both of these muscles. They are effectively together a single motor unit, and there is only one motor neuron that goes into it. Invertebrates are weird.
Simon N Sponberg: They have the same mass and the same moment arm.
Simon N Sponberg: They have the same macroscopic organization, meaning, like, the panacea angle and everything like that. And they have the same force length and force velocity curves.
Simon N Sponberg: Pretty much.
Simon N Sponberg: Okay? So everything we characterize a muscle with says these two muscles are exactly the same.
Simon N Sponberg: But then you do the work loops.
Simon N Sponberg: And you've had work loops. Here's the work loops for the two muscle. One is a break, and one is bifunctional, and actually produces net positive work.
Simon N Sponberg: So, one's entirely dissipating energy, and one is producing a large amount of positive work.
Simon N Sponberg: Why? What's different about these two things?
Simon N Sponberg: That's what Travis wanted to discuss. And what he hypothesized is that this difference between a brake and a motor-like muscle is maybe there's something different about the molecular spacing. But if that's true, it can only be present during the dynamic conditions of that muscle contracting.
Simon N Sponberg: Because the steady-state properties, the length… force-velocity curve and the force-length curve, have to be the same.
Simon N Sponberg: So, he took cockroaches to Argon, and he shot x-rays
Simon N Sponberg: the particle accelerator through them, and he measured the lattice spacing. And John Kuhn will talk a little bit more about how we do this, but one of these dots, the 10 dot, corresponds to the lattice spacing between the thick filaments, between the myosin planes, and he'll talk a little bit about why this is the case in just a minute. But for now, I want you to know that you can make these measurements, and I want you to tell you about the kinds of things you can do with those measurements. So by measuring the distance of that
Simon N Sponberg: first peak in the diffraction muscle, one from the motor, one's from the brake up there. We can tell how… if there's a difference in the spacing at the level of a few nanometers.
Simon N Sponberg: And here's what he did. He measured the lattice spacing as a function of stretching the muscle to different strains, and just holding it at those different lengths. And what he noticed was something really interesting.
Simon N Sponberg: Muscle 178 has a slightly tighter lattice. At all lengths, it's basically… before it's activated, the muscle is 1 nanometer tighter in its lattice spacing change. This is only a 2% difference, but it's a really important thing because a 1 nanometer difference in spacing on a free energy landscape is a big difference in binding probability.
Simon N Sponberg: And here's the cool thing, he then activated these two muscles like you would for a force-length curve, right? He did isometric activation experiments.
Simon N Sponberg: And he activated them, and an interesting thing happened.
Simon N Sponberg: The muscle on the left, I like to call it the morning… it's not a morning person. It has to get up and stretch. It stretches out the lattice spacing, and it actually increases its lattice spacing as it's activated. Whereas the one on the right is a morning person. It's ready to go. It's… as soon as you activate, the lattice spacing stays the same.
Simon N Sponberg: So this explains why they have the same steady-state properties, because when you activate these to an isometric condition.
Simon N Sponberg: They have the same lattice spacing.
Simon N Sponberg: But if you're gonna go back and forth between contracting and relaxing, the lattice spacing on the muscle on the left is gonna change, and the lattice spacing on the muscle on the right is not gonna change. And Travis was able to show, then, that what's actually happening is the muscle on the left, during a work loop.
Simon N Sponberg: The mean change in the lattice spacing is actually undergoing a larger excursion in the activated muscle on the left than on the right.
Simon N Sponberg: And it's undergoing a 1 nanometer larger change in lattice spacing than the muscle on the right.
Simon N Sponberg: And that change in lattice spacing occurs right at the time when that muscle would need to produce larger amounts of force in order to act like a motor.
Simon N Sponberg: And, so what the basic story here is that one of these is already constrained, and then expands out, and that allows it to do more work, and one is already at its extended point, and produces less binding, and does net negative work because of it. And Travis actually did a bunch of spatially explicit modeling about this using some of the models that we've talked about previously that Bert Tanner talked about.
Simon N Sponberg: I'll skip through this and just say we fit a bunch of parameters to that, and here's the…
Simon N Sponberg: I'll skip that slide. And the take-home is that he was actually able to show in that model that a 1 nanometer difference in spacing in the model could actually produce work loops that had different directions.
Simon N Sponberg: So a 1 nanometer spacing change in the lattice spacing can be the difference between having a motor and having a brake.
Simon N Sponberg: Okay, so that's the kind of thing that we can do with X-ray diffraction, and I just want to summarize the main points before Jiangkun takes over. So, there's this idea of using time-resolved X-ray diffraction to give us basically a real… a high-speed video of the molecular dynamics in living muscle, at the same time that you can measure force at the macroscale.
Simon N Sponberg: And so this gives us accessibility that we don't have in other experiments, and in the experiment that I was talking about, a single nanometer spacing difference between two cockroach muscles provides a mechanism for how one is a motor and one is a brake, and that can be recapitulated in our spatially explicit models, showing that this one nanometer spacing could actually account for this difference in macroscopic function.
Simon N Sponberg: Okay, so that's your biological example to take forward. I now want to turn it over to Jiangkun, and he's going to take you through a deeper dive in what X-ray diffraction is, how you would do this measurement, why does it work, a little bit of the physics behind it, and also how you would go and do this experimentally.
Simon N Sponberg: But before I do that, are there any questions?
Simon N Sponberg: For me.
Simon N Sponberg: All perfectly clear. Everyone's an expert on top broaches now.
Simon N Sponberg: Well, if you have questions as we go along, please interrupt Jiangkun and ask him and Casey, and Jiangkun will also have several points in time now where he's going to be pausing his workshop and actually making you do some work, because it is a workshop. You have to do some positive work here, okay? So…
Simon N Sponberg: Don't break down.
Simon N Sponberg: Motor through it, and have fun with Junk.
Jiangkun Wei: Thank you.
Casey King: Great puns, Simon, that needed to be acknowledged. That was very good.
Jiangkun Wei: Okay, let me share my screen.
Jiangkun Wei: Ken, everybody hears me.
Jiangkun Wei: Can you see my screen now?
Jiangkun Wei: Yes, we can.
Casey King: And Jiangkun, it's great.
Jiangkun Wei: Okay, thank you.
Jiangkun Wei: Oh.
Jiangkun Wei: So, good morning. I'm Jiangkun Wei. I'm the postdoc in Simon's Lab in the School of Physical Storage Attack, and we have… also have Casey Kin here, who's our PhD student. So today, Casey and I will introduce X-ray diffraction as a tool
Jiangkun Wei: For starting striated muscle.
Jiangkun Wei: Our goal is not to turn you into a crystal… crystallographer in one section.
Jiangkun Wei: Instead, we want to leave you with three practical skills. To recognize the main features of an X-ray diffraction pattern, to connect those features to the structures in the sarcomere, and to understand how an experiment is carried out at the synchrotron beamline.
Jiangkun Wei: I'm going to give you some background information first, and then walk you through the basic X-ray diffraction principles, and then introduce the X-ray diffraction from myofilaments. And finally, Casey will walk you through the experiment details and how we analyze an X-ray diffraction image.
Jiangkun Wei: So let's get some background information first.
Jiangkun Wei: Over the summer, I believe those of you have very good understanding of this hierarchical structure of the muscle.
Jiangkun Wei: However, recognizing these structural levels is different from knowing them, their quantitative geometry. For example, do you know how far apart are the thick and thin filaments?
Jiangkun Wei: And how do these dimensions change when the muscle is activated or stretched?
Jiangkun Wei: So to understand how molecular structure determines muscle function, we need methods that can measure these dimensions at the myofilament level.
Jiangkun Wei: So how can we obtain this structural information?
Jiangkun Wei: One way to study the structure at the myofilament level is by using electron microscopy.
Jiangkun Wei: These electron micrographs show insect five months, so in transverse and longitudinal cross-sections.
Jiangkun Wei: In the transverse cross-section, we can directly see the regular arrangement of thick and thin filaments.
Jiangkun Wei: And in the longitudinal section, we can see the repeating sarcomere structure and the organization of the cross bridges as little 2.
Jiangkun Wei: to big image. Electron microscopy provides high-resolution, real-space images, so it is therefore exceptionally valuable for identifying individual structures and establishing the geometrical model of the myofilament lattice.
Jiangkun Wei: However, before we interpret the dimensions measured from these images, we should consider how the samples were prepared.
Jiangkun Wei: So the conventional electron microscopic… microscopic has several limitations for studying muscle under physiological conditions.
Jiangkun Wei: Sample preparation commonly requires fixation, dehydration, standing, and thin sectioning.
Jiangkun Wei: These procedures can shrink or distort the myofilament lattice, so the dimensions in this final image
Jiangkun Wei: May differ from those in hydrated, functioning muscle.
Jiangkun Wei: In addition, conventional electron micrographs are usually static snapshots.
Jiangkun Wei: It is difficult to use them to follow rapid structural changes in the same muscle while it's contracting.
Jiangkun Wei: This is where X-ray diffraction becomes particularly useful.
Jiangkun Wei: X-rays can pass through hydrated biological tissue, allowing us to study the intact muscle under control physiological conditions.
Jiangkun Wei: The example as shown here, we can put a live moth or a living muscle tissues directly in the VIN blind.
Jiangkun Wei: So we can change the muscle length, activate the muscle, measure the force, and record diffraction patterns simultaneously.
Jiangkun Wei: Another important advantage of the X-ray diffraction is that it can recall the structural dynamics of muscle on a millisecond timescale.
Jiangkun Wei: With a bright synchrotron X-ray source and a fast detector, we can collect a sequence of diffraction patterns while the muscle is contracting. This allows us to observe how the molecular structure changes over time.
Jiangkun Wei: And to compare those changes directly with muscle length and force, as shown in these dynamic videos. So this video provides an example of such a time-resolved measurement. As you watch it, notice that the diffraction pattern is not static.
Jiangkun Wei: Some reflections change their position, although very small amount positions.
Jiangkun Wei: And… while others changes their intensities.
Jiangkun Wei: These changes tell us that the spacing and organization of myofilaments are changing as the muscle functions, which we'll talk about it later.
Jiangkun Wei: And Simon sometimes said if you can see the changes with your naked eyes, there are major changes happening at the molecular scales.
Jiangkun Wei: So before we move on to the principles of diffraction, let us ask a fundamental question. What is an X-ray?
Jiangkun Wei: X-rays are the same type of physical phenomenon as the visible lines, the microwaves we use to hit food, and the radio waves used for communication. They are all electromagnetic waves.
Jiangkun Wei: They differ mainly in their wavelengths and frequencies.
Jiangkun Wei: The X-ray used in diffraction experiments typically have wavelength of approximately 0.1 to 0.2 nanometers.
Jiangkun Wei: or one or two angstroms. This wavelength is comparable to atomic scales distance, so making X-rays particularly useful for investigating molecular structure.
Jiangkun Wei: Because X-rays can penetrate matters.
Jiangkun Wei: They have many applications.
Jiangkun Wei: In medical and security CD scans, x-rays pass through the body and your luggage to detect internal structures. While in diffraction, however, we measure how X-rays are scattered at different angles to obtain the structural information.
Jiangkun Wei: It has played an essential important role in determining biological structures.
Jiangkun Wei: One of the most famous examples is the determination of the double helical structure of DNA.
Jiangkun Wei: The pattern shown here is known as Photo 51. It was produced by Rosalind Franklin and Raymond Gosselin.
Jiangkun Wei: The characteristic X-ray pattern provides strong evidence that DNA has a helical structure.
Jiangkun Wei: The diffraction pattern is not a direct photograph of a DNA molecular.
Jiangkun Wei: The positions and spacing of the reflections.
Jiangkun Wei: Can provide quantitative information about the dimensions of the helix.
Jiangkun Wei: Muscle is also an ordered fibrous system, so we can use the same general principle to study the arrangement of these myofilaments.
Jiangkun Wei: Now, we will build the physical ideas needed to read a diffraction pattern.
Jiangkun Wei: Let's first look at what diffraction means.
Jiangkun Wei: Diffraction is the deviation of waves from straight-line propagation.
Jiangkun Wei: Due to an obstacle through an aperture.
Jiangkun Wei: I think you can better under this phenomenon by looking at the water waves. In this video, the water waves deviate from straight-line propagation and spread after passing through the narrow opening.
Jiangkun Wei: This is diffraction.
Jiangkun Wei: And sound waves also follow this property. If you are standing in the left room, imagine this is left room, and you're standing here, and someone is talking in the right room. You can still hear his voice anywhere in the left room, because the sound waves will spread.
Jiangkun Wei: So water waves, sound waves, and electromagnetic waves all follow these spreading properties.
Jiangkun Wei: However, spreading alone does not explain the bright and dark features of a diffraction pattern. So in this video, a man with nuclei moves two balls on the water surface. Each ball
Jiangkun Wei: Acts as a wave source and produces a series of circular waves.
Jiangkun Wei: As the waves spread outwards, they meet and overlap.
Jiangkun Wei: They did not simply collide and stop. Instead, their amplitudes combined. In some regions, the two waves reinforce each other's and produce larger waves. In some other regions, they oppose each other's and produce smaller waves.
Jiangkun Wei: This creates a regular interference patterns on the water surface.
Jiangkun Wei: So why do the waves reinforce each other in some regions but cancel in others?
Jiangkun Wei: The answer depends on their relative face.
Jiangkun Wei: You can see here.
Jiangkun Wei: In the last schematic shown here.
Jiangkun Wei: There are two waves, and the lower, the lower schematic shows their combined waves.
Jiangkun Wei: So, when the two phase… when the two waves are in phase, it means that the pigs.
Jiangkun Wei: Meets the pigs, the troughs meets troughs.
Jiangkun Wei: the amplitude… Add together and produce a stronger signal.
Jiangkun Wei: But in the middle schematic shows these destructive interference.
Jiangkun Wei: The two waves are out of phase.
Jiangkun Wei: The pig… Of one wave meets the 12th.
Jiangkun Wei: Of the other. And their amplitudes reduce Or completely cancel each other.
Jiangkun Wei: So, on the right side, the face of two waves is somewhere between, so…
Jiangkun Wei: Between the constructive and destructive interference, so leading to partial interference.
Jiangkun Wei: The classical Jans double-slit experiment can provide a simple demonstration of how the face differences produce a pattern of bright and dark regions on the detectors.
Jiangkun Wei: In this experiment, an incoming wave passes through two narrow slips.
Jiangkun Wei: Each slit acts as a new wave source, similar to the two balls in the water wave video. So at the center of the screen, the distance from two slits
Jiangkun Wei: Ariel?
Jiangkun Wei: The waves arrive in phase and produce a brighter fringe.
Jiangkun Wei: At the odd position, the two waves travel at different distances.
Jiangkun Wei: When the path difference
Jiangkun Wei: is half a wavelength, so they are out of phase. They interfere destructively and produce a dark fringe.
Jiangkun Wei: This alternating pattern of bright and dark fridge is an interference pattern.
Jiangkun Wei: Well, in Jan's experiment, the two slits act as sources of waves that later interfere. But in the X-ray diffraction experiment, this is electron.
Jiangkun Wei: This video shows how an X-ray interacts with an electron. An X-ray is an electromagnetic wave. Its oscillating electric field causes the electron to oscillate.
Jiangkun Wei: Because oscillating charged particles, and then it emits another electromagnetic radiation.
Jiangkun Wei: So the electron produces new scattered X-ray waves in many directions.
Jiangkun Wei: So this schematic shows X-rays scattered from particles separated by a distant D.
Jiangkun Wei: The important point is that the phase relationship between the scattered wave
Jiangkun Wei: depends on the direction in which we observe them, the diffraction angle, we say.
Jiangkun Wei: On the left side, the path difference between the two scattered waves is the whole number of wavelengths.
Jiangkun Wei: the lower wave passes through one wavelength and then the other wavelengths. So, when they scatter out.
Jiangkun Wei: their face, their wave up, pretty much in phase, so their amplitudes will add together and produce high intensity. This is constructive interference. On the other hand.
Jiangkun Wei: on the right.
Jiangkun Wei: The path difference forces the wave to arrive out of phase. You can see out of phase here. The amplitudes will partially or completely cancel, producing low intensity. This is destructive interference.
Jiangkun Wei: Therefore, the same periodic structure can produce strong scattering in some directions and weak scattering in other directions.
Jiangkun Wei: In this video, the X-ray beam interacts with the periodic array of scattering particles. Each particle produces a scattered X-ray wave.
Jiangkun Wei: At most angles.
Jiangkun Wei: The scattered waves have different phase and largely cancel one another, therefore the diffraction intensity is wave. However, at certain specific angles, the waves arrive in phase and reinforce one another, producing a strong diffraction beam.
Jiangkun Wei: This strong diffraction pegs.
Jiangkun Wei: all care only at the angle where constructed interference is satisfied. These specific angles are called Brax angles.
Jiangkun Wei: So what is special about this angle? What geometric condition allows the scattered waves to arrive in phase? This condition is described by Bragg's law.
Jiangkun Wei: Here, we represent a periodic structure by a series of parallel lattice planes separated by a distant V.
Jiangkun Wei: Consider two x-rays, the first, the upper two x-rays.
Jiangkun Wei: scattered from neighboring planes. The X-rate, scattered from the lower plains
Jiangkun Wei: travels a longer distance. The additional distance is one wavelength.
Jiangkun Wei: Before scattering and, and other wavelengths after scattering.
Jiangkun Wei: So, consider the X-ray from the third pen.
Jiangkun Wei: It travels even longer distance, so the two wavelengths. One wavelength is one number. It travels two wavelengths before scattering, and another two wavelengths after scattering. So generally speaking, constructive interference occurs when its path difference
Jiangkun Wei: equals an integer number of wavelengths. So this is how, Bragg's Law come out.
Jiangkun Wei: So this is Braggloss. As a reminder, lambda is the X-ray wavelengths
Jiangkun Wei: N is the diffraction order.
Jiangkun Wei: the theta.
Jiangkun Wei: is the angle between the X-ray beam and the lattice plane, while the angle measured on the detection in the X-ray diffraction pattern is actually 2 theta.
Jiangkun Wei: So, therefore, if we know the X-ray diffraction, X-ray wavelength and measured the diffraction angle, we can calculate the spacing of the periodic structure.
Jiangkun Wei: In other words, each diffraction pick provides information about a specific structural spacing in the samples.
Jiangkun Wei: So the principle, we have more rigorous mathematical theories for the X-ray diffractions, but I think for most of you, the main takeaway here is
Jiangkun Wei: All materials can scatter X-rays. A sufficiently regular periodic structure causes waves scatter from successive repeats to interfere constructively at specific angles, producing distinct reflection on the detector.
Jiangkun Wei: Disorder structures generally produce diffuse scatterings.
Jiangkun Wei: And each reflection would correspond to a periodic structure spacing in the sample.
Jiangkun Wei: In the X-ray wavelength, if the X-ray wavelength is known, the position of the reflection can be used with Bragg's law to calculate that spacings.
Jiangkun Wei: So, after we have some impression on the general physical principle of the diffraction, now in Section 3, we will apply these principles to myofilament in muscles.
Jiangkun Wei: a muscle… And it's not a perfect three-dimensional crystal.
Jiangkun Wei: However, it contains highly ordered and repeating molecular structures, so it can be viewed as a neo-crystalline or quasi-crystalline material.
Jiangkun Wei: This image shows a cross-section of the muscle fiber. A single muscle fiber contains many myofibrils, each approximately a few micrometers in diameter. If we zoom in further.
Jiangkun Wei: You can see that the thick and thin filaments are arranged in a regular hexagonal lattice, and this is, in effect, a two-dimensional crystal.
Jiangkun Wei: The orange circle represents thick filament in this schematic, and the blue circles represent thin filament. Because this arrangement repeats over many filaments, the scattered X-rays can interfere constructively and produce distinct reflection.
Jiangkun Wei: Now let's consider what happened in a real muscle experiment.
Jiangkun Wei: When an incident beam passes through a periodic area of vertical fibers, It diffracts into secondary waves.
Jiangkun Wei: And it is reflected on the detector.
Jiangkun Wei: On the detector, the vertical direction, we call it meridian, And the horizontal… Axis is the equator.
Jiangkun Wei: Equatorial reflection arise from the lateral arrangement of the thick and thin filaments. They are usually the strongest reflection you will observe in the X-ray diffraction image, and can provide information about the distances across the myofilament lattice.
Jiangkun Wei: The X-ray beam does not pass through only one myofibrium, it passes through a very large number of myofibrils simultaneously.
Jiangkun Wei: When viewed in cross-sections, their filament lattices may be rotated by different angles around that axis, so when shooting an accurate beam on a muscle fiber or bundle, the beam will illuminate a large number of myofibril.
Jiangkun Wei: With many different rotational orientations simultaneously.
Jiangkun Wei: So the final diffraction pattern is rotationally averaged.
Jiangkun Wei: To analyze the myofilament lattice, we first need a way to describe its repeating geometry, and we usually use
Jiangkun Wei: the unit cell to describe it, which is the smallest repeating unit, that can be translated to generate the entire lattice. So although the muscle
Jiangkun Wei: is in Hisacano.
Jiangkun Wei: shape arrangement. The smallest repeating unicell is actually this shape we show here. So…
Jiangkun Wei: We use Miller indices to label different families of parallel planes.
Jiangkun Wei: In two dimensions, the indices are written as H and K.
Jiangkun Wei: So, to determine the indices, we first need to find where planes intersect with A and B axis. A and B represent two dimensions of this lattice, these unit cells.
Jiangkun Wei: and then take their reciprocals, and we find the smallest integers, that is H and K. For example, in these first examples, the plane intersect both axis A and B, A and B, at one unit.
Jiangkun Wei: this intersects one unit, and the other plane intersect A in another one unit, so they are one one plane.
Jiangkun Wei: And in the second example, the plane intersects A-axis at one and half of the unit, and B axis at one unit. So taking their reciprocal as 2-1.
Jiangkun Wei: In the final example, the plane intersects the A-axis, In one unit.
Jiangkun Wei: but it is parallel to the B… Axis.
Jiangkun Wei: So, the… So… The reciprocal is zero.
Jiangkun Wei: Therefore, they are one-old plants.
Jiangkun Wei: So, do you have any question about the notation of the planes?
Jiangkun Wei: So, we are going to apply this notation, Miller indices.
Jiangkun Wei: to the myofilament lattice. So, this is the myofilament lattice we saw earlier. The orange circle represents the thick filaments, and the blue circles represent thin filaments. The vector A and B defines the unit cells.
Jiangkun Wei: So, let's do some practice here, take a pose. Using the rules from the previous slide, let's make a pose and try to draw the 1-0, 11, and 2O plans.
Jiangkun Wei: For age families, you can…
Jiangkun Wei: Draw two parallel lines to… allows you to identify both the orientation and the spacing between the planes.
Jiangkun Wei: I think we can take…
Jiangkun Wei: 2 minutes post here. Everybody just tried to draw it, and we'll show… and I will show you the answer after 2 minutes.
Jiangkun Wei: Hey, Isabel.
Jiangkun Wei: 2 minutes.
Jiangkun Wei: So, let me show you the answer.
Casey King: Wait, wait, don't… wait, does anybody… do we want to see if anybody has an answer? So, you did see one answer there, but we could see if anybody wants to chime in and see if they figured out the indices, or if they can draw on the screen, or something like that.
Jiangkun Wei: Oh, sure.
Casey King: Any volunteers?
Casey King: Okay, well, I guess we tried, so, you can go ahead and show the answers, Jiangkun.
Jiangkun Wei: Okay, here we place the origin at the… this left origin thick filaments, this is vector A, this is factor B of the unit cells, M.
Jiangkun Wei: Let's begin with Bondo plans.
Jiangkun Wei: So this… this is one of planes, because this plane intersects A vector in one unit, but it's parallel to the B axis, so it's 1O.
Jiangkun Wei: Those never intersect with the… Access B.
Jiangkun Wei: And… Let's consider it.
Jiangkun Wei: This plane's too old.
Jiangkun Wei: So, this plane… F intersect as intersect 8.
Jiangkun Wei: in half.
Jiangkun Wei: But they're also parallel to the vector B, so it never intersects.
Jiangkun Wei: Axis B.
Jiangkun Wei: So this is two airplanes.
Jiangkun Wei: So, you need to remember, it intersects the axis A in half, and we need to take the reciprocal for the first number, so this is 2.0.
Jiangkun Wei: And the hardest one might be the 1-1.
Jiangkun Wei: Because 1-1… Plans intersect.
Jiangkun Wei: the Axis.
Jiangkun Wei: this… they're… they are plane families, they're parallel to each other with the… with the consistent, spacings. So Won planes intersect both A and B,
Jiangkun Wei: at one unit. So these are actually one one thing. And they can actually rotate, because the…
Jiangkun Wei: you can represent in a cell, like, AB or BA.
Jiangkun Wei: So, so, this planes can kind of rotate.
Jiangkun Wei: Okay.
Jiangkun Wei: Now that we… now we will learn how to convert the position of the reflection in the real structure, to… into a real structure information.
Jiangkun Wei: So this is the detector here, and this is the muscle. The schematic show an x-ray.
Jiangkun Wei: Go through the muscle and diffract.
Jiangkun Wei: onto the detector. Actually, the angle is pretty small.
Jiangkun Wei: The spacing between the muscle and the detector, usually at the scale of meters, like 3 to 5 meters.
Jiangkun Wei: But… The distance between the reflections to the detector center is millimeters, so it's a very small diffraction angle.
Jiangkun Wei: Okay, let S be the distance from the beam center to the center of the reflection, and let L
Jiangkun Wei: be the sample detector distance. From this geometry, we know that Tangent to theta.
Jiangkun Wei: 2 theta is the diffraction angle here, equals to S over L,
Jiangkun Wei: And because it is a very small, diffraction angles, so with…
Jiangkun Wei: the small angle approximation tangent 2 theta equals to sine 2 theta equals to 2 theta, and finally 2 sine theta. And if you substitute 2 sines theta into the original Bragg's law.
Jiangkun Wei: We don't need to measure the theta, we only need to measure the spacing.
Jiangkun Wei: on the screen, between the reflection and the center of the detector. So that is the updated Bragg's Law equations.
Jiangkun Wei: So, this equation tells us that the detector distance S And, real space…
Jiangkun Wei: spacing D. This is… D is the spacing put in the real space myofilament lattice.
Jiangkun Wei: So, they are inversely related.
Jiangkun Wei: a re… a reflection Farther away from the center.
Jiangkun Wei: correspond to a smaller structure spacing in the real muscles. So, now, you will need to, you will use this relationship yourself to measure a real reflection spot in a diffraction image.
Jiangkun Wei: Okay, this is our workshop time, practice time.
Jiangkun Wei: So, I will have… Victoria to divide you into 3 breakout rooms. Each group
Jiangkun Wei: We'll measure one equilibrial reflections.
Jiangkun Wei: Something like this.
Jiangkun Wei: On the right side of the pattern.
Jiangkun Wei: Group 1, We'll analyze the closest reflection to the center.
Jiangkun Wei: to the center, and Group 2 will analyze the middle reflection, and Group 3 will analyze the third farthest reflection. So, you can first locate the center of the direct beam.
Jiangkun Wei: and which is the center of this dark rota… circular region, and then measure this from the center to the center of the reflection pix you assigned. So you can insert a line using the PowerPoint.
Jiangkun Wei: And you can directly read the length of the inserted lines under the shape format here, but this is not the real length. You need to convert it with this scale part, and with the measure length, you can calculate
Jiangkun Wei: The real space, the spacing of the…
Jiangkun Wei: corresponding filament lattice using these equations, because we have known the wavelength and the distance between the sample to the detector. And you can also try to calculate the diffraction angles using these equations and convert it in the… from the radian
Jiangkun Wei: Unit to the degree unit.
Jiangkun Wei: Okay, I think we can have… A minutes for that?
Jiangkun Wei: victoria, can you help me? Yeah, thank you.
Victoria Wood: Yes, alright, 8 minutes.
Victoria Wood: Sounds good.
Jiangkun Wei: Perfect.
Jiangkun Wei: That was me early.
Jiangkun Wei: No, I'm sleeping.
Jiangkun Wei: Sweet.
Jiangkun Wei: What's the name?
Jiangkun Wei: Awesome.
Victoria Wood: You're doing a great job, Jiangkun. This is such complex material to present.
Victoria Wood: I appreciate it.
Casey King: Yeah, this presentation and this, like, content material, even though I've spent a lot of time with it, it's still, like… it still breaks your brain, because, like, every image is reciprocal space, so it's, like, it's just not intuitive at all.
Victoria Wood: It's just…
Casey King: Doesn't… it doesn't always make sense.
Victoria Wood: But this is… this is one of the better explanations I've ever seen of it, so thank you. Great.
Casey King: Yeah, John Kuhn's done really well.
Victoria Wood: I'll send out a one-minute warning, and then there'll be 60 seconds for people to join back once they close.
Casey King: You pulled up this slide, Jiangkun, and I thought you were about to hand them the answers again.
Casey King: They definitely have to share the answers this time.
Victoria Wood: Alright, I'm gonna go ahead and close the rooms so they'll have… 60 seconds to return.
Katrina Moore: Let's see, I got 12.63 millimeters.
Katrina Moore: Oh, whoops.
Victoria Wood: We'll need that answer in a second.
Katrina Moore: Not in workout rooms anymore.
Victoria Wood: Alright, everybody should be back now.
Casey King: Okay, awesome. Is… is Group 1 ready to share their… their answers for the 1-0 spacing?
Casey King: The lattice spacing and the small angle.
Martie Fairchild (she/her): Kind of. We are… I… we basically… Calculated the width.
Martie Fairchild (she/her): the S, and then I quickly just did the D, but I'm not…
Martie Fairchild (she/her): 100% sure if I'm correct, so maybe.
Martie Fairchild (she/her): I can share, and then you can let me know if it's correct.
Casey King: Don't be afraid to, you know, don't be afraid to give a wrong answer. There's a lot of unit changes in here, you're dealing with, like.
Casey King: Millimeters, and then nanometers, and it's confusing, so don't worry about it, just go ahead and share.
Martie Fairchild (she/her): Okay, so, on…
Martie Fairchild (she/her): the slides, we got our width, since we're Group 1, to be 0.77 inches, and then when we converted that, that was roughly 7-ish millimeters, and then when we plugged it in with the known lambda and L, I got the D to be 43.5?
Martie Fairchild (she/her): Thoughts, comments, concerns?
Casey King: 43.5, and what are your units?
Martie Fairchild (she/her): Nanometers.
Casey King: I think that's pretty close. Jiangkun, do you have it animated where you can show the… the first answer?
Casey King: Okay, there you go, you were very close. That's perfect. You know, it's an approximation on these slides.
Martie Fairchild (she/her): Yeah, probably rounding errors as well for…
Casey King: Yeah, no worries. No, that was great.
Casey King: Okay, next group.
Casey King: Oh, Jiangkun, you're, you're muted. You're muted.
Jiangkun Wei: Sorry. So, so this is not the very exactly answer. I also used the PowerPoint to do the measurements, but it's very close. It means that your measurement is correct.
Jiangkun Wei: And we will have more, better software to measure the real… process the real data, in case we show you later.
Jiangkun Wei: I think you got a very good result. It's pretty close.
Jiangkun Wei: And, Group 2.
Katrina Moore: Yeah, we only made it as far as calculating the distance from the center to that.
Jiangkun Wei: That's okay.
Katrina Moore: And we haven't converted it to nanometers yet, but I think we got about 12.63 millimeters.
Katrina Moore: For that mission.
Casey King: So then I guess the question… a question would be, since we're in reciprocal space, if that reflection is further
Casey King: by a certain amount, then what would the nanometer spacing then be? Would it be larger than the D10 nanometer spacing, or, smaller?
Katrina Moore: I guess, larger?
Casey King: So…
Katrina Moore: I'm staying smaller.
Casey King: Yeah, yeah. So, it's… it's… this is… it's really confusing when you look at X-ray diffraction images. So, Jiangkun, go ahead and share the… the answer for that… that one.
Casey King: Yeah. So it's smaller… oh, you already… you spoiled the next one. It's smaller because,
Casey King: we're in reciprocal space, so everything that's further away from the center of the image, in the X-ray diffraction image.
Casey King: actually represents a spacing in real physical space that's smaller, and all the reflections that are really close represent a large physical spacing. So it's like, it's kind of counterintuitive, and you'll stare at these images forever if you decide to do any X-ray diffraction experiments, and your brain will break, because you're just trying to see what does each reflection mean.
Casey King: So yeah. Group 3, go ahead.
Amulya Kadaba: Maybe I can share what answer that I got? Sure.
Amulya Kadaba: I think… got around 7.8 nanometers.
Amulya Kadaba: And I calculated the radians, I didn't get the degrees.
Amulya Kadaba: But for medians, I got .013.
Jiangkun Wei: Okay, that's the… I think because you're measuring the 2-0, and it is kind of the sec… this late.
Jiangkun Wei: this plane. So, the distance should be somewhere Half of the 1-0.
Jiangkun Wei: Right, can you understand? Yeah.
Jiangkun Wei: Okay, that is… sorry, I put the wrong unit here. It's nanometer. Yeah, it's nanometer, so it's…
Jiangkun Wei: Kind of close to the half, right?
Jiangkun Wei: of D10.
Jiangkun Wei: Yeah, and I should… I should plot the detail here between… the distance is between these planes and these planes.
Jiangkun Wei: Oh, here's the tool. We are looking at different angles. We can also use this as a tool, so…
Jiangkun Wei: This is still smaller even than Won planes.
Casey King: Yeah, and I would say that's still good, because you were on the right… you were in the right magnitude. You were still, like, 7 nanometers… you're off by less than an order of magnitude, so it's… it's… that's okay. And the radians answer was pretty close to the degrees answer I just tried to calculate today.
Jiangkun Wei: degrees, right?
Casey King: real quick from your radiance answer. So, yeah, and you can see these are really small angles, like, less than 1 degree. That's why it's called small angle X-ray diffraction. So, thank you guys for everyone who spoke and gave their answers bravely, so…
Casey King: Alright, Jiangkun, go ahead and carry on.
Jiangkun Wei: Thank you, yeah. And so the basic idea of this… you can see, as Casey just mentioned, when the reflection is further away.
Jiangkun Wei: the real, space… ladder spacing is smaller. So this reverse, relationship is the basic idea behind precipical space.
Jiangkun Wei: The scales in the real muscle lattice and the diffraction spot is reversed.
Jiangkun Wei: So, on the previous slide, we used a precision of the reflection to determine the ladder spacing.
Jiangkun Wei: Now let's consider their intensity, and intensity means how bright each reflection is.
Jiangkun Wei: is kind of more abstracted than the spacing, but I'll try to explain this in an easier way. The X-rays are scattered mainly by electrons in the muscle X-ray diffraction, so for each reflection.
Jiangkun Wei: The scattered waves from all electron density and the repeating unit are added together, including their phases.
Jiangkun Wei: Therefore, a strong reflection means the scattered waves reinforce each other at a spatial frequency, and a weak reflection means that they partially cancel each other, so it doesn't mean that
Jiangkun Wei: if the reflection is weak, it doesn't mean that there are less protein lines on the particularly lattice planes. It's the…
Jiangkun Wei: problem of how they reinforce or cancel each other's. So here, we should compare the relative intensity within each pattern.
Jiangkun Wei: Because the displace scale may differ between different muscles. So, in the insect-blind muscle.
Jiangkun Wei: The 1O and 2O reflection are prominent, while the 1-1 reflection is… Relatively weak.
Jiangkun Wei: This is the vertebrate skeletal muscle. The 1-0 and 11 reflections are dominant.
Jiangkun Wei: while the… while you can… you cannot… you can barely see the TL effect, and it's much weaker.
Jiangkun Wei: So…
Jiangkun Wei: Both muscles, both skeletal muscles, have Hisaconal filament lattices, so why are their intensities so different? And the reason is that the thin filaments actually occupy different positions within the lattice.
Jiangkun Wei: If you look at the lattice on the thin insect flight muscle.
Jiangkun Wei: Again, the orange circles represent the thick filament, and the blue circle represent the thin one, and the thick, you can see there in hisagonal lattice. Each thick filament is surrounded by 6 thin filaments.
Jiangkun Wei: However, each… in the form of each thin filament is shared by two thick filaments. This thin filament is shared by these two, but not that two. They're too far away. So, the thin filament to thick filament ratio is six thin…
Jiangkun Wei: To 2, so it… you need to divide it 6 by 2, so it's 3 to 1 thin-thick filament ratios.
Jiangkun Wei: And this 3-to-1 arrangement creates additional electron density modulation between the rows of thick filaments.
Jiangkun Wei: Essentially, it means that
Jiangkun Wei: If you look at 10, their plans are kind of in face with each other, so they have strong, stronger reflection. But if you look at 101,
Jiangkun Wei: This plane is in phase with this plane.
Jiangkun Wei: But there is other parallel planes here, and those planes, those particles here, It's in half phase.
Jiangkun Wei: Of the… of this 1-1 plane.
Jiangkun Wei: So they will… this will kind of interfere the reflection and cancel it. To simply say this, the arrangement matters.
Jiangkun Wei: But if you look at the vertebral muscles, they also have the hexagonal arrangement, but the thin filament occupies at different
Jiangkun Wei: positions. Here, the thin filaments are located at Triagonal position, so…
Jiangkun Wei: This is thin filaments, and it's surrounded by, like, 3…
Jiangkun Wei: thick filaments. So, each thick filament
Jiangkun Wei: Each thick filament is, again, surrounded by 6 thin filaments, but each thin filament in the vertebrate muscle is shared by 3 thick filaments, so…
Jiangkun Wei: This ratio is 6 divided by 3, so giving 2 to 1 thick and thick filament ratios. So in this arrangement, the
Jiangkun Wei: scatter… Weight is… is kind of different, and if you look at 2-0, playing 2L.
Jiangkun Wei: So there are barely… thin filaments or thick filaments sit at these two planes, so you can barely see that there are no molecular to scatter the electron.
Jiangkun Wei: So…
Jiangkun Wei: I want to… the intensity is kind of abstracted, but I want to give you this main takeaway, as the reflection positions can tell us the spacing and the reflection intensity
Jiangkun Wei: Tell us about the distribution of protein mass within the lattice, and it's affected by the lattice arrangement.
Jiangkun Wei: And so far, we have viewed the myofilament lattice in cross-section and focused on the apultarial reflection. Those reflections mainly report the lateral arrangement of thick and thin filaments. However, muscle is ordered in three dimensions.
Jiangkun Wei: And for some muscle with very near-crystalline structures, like instant fly muscle, they are very ordered and can produce more diffractions
Jiangkun Wei: beyond, the equatorial lines. So here we're looking along the length of myofibrio.
Jiangkun Wei: This image shows approximately half of the sarcomere extending from the Z digs to the M lines. So in the overlapping regions, many myosin hats
Jiangkun Wei: We'll project from the thick to the… from the thick filaments and interact with the thin filaments.
Jiangkun Wei: And importantly, these filaments are not a smooth rod. The protein components repeat regularly along their 5-axis, and both
Jiangkun Wei: actin and myosin, both thin or thick vermin have helical organizations. So, therefore, the muscle contains axial and helical periodic periodicity, in addition to the lateral spacing.
Jiangkun Wei: So, there are also some connective proteins, like neodyx, like titan, and they're also periodic structures. All these periodic structures can produce meridiano refraction and other layer lines in the diffraction patterns.
Jiangkun Wei: So this is the Meridian online.
Jiangkun Wei: The reflection on the Meridiano line, we call it Meridiano reflection. And this reflections, we call it layer lines.
Jiangkun Wei: Some layer lines are correlated with the myosin, so we call it myosin layer line. Some layer lines are correlated with the actin, we call it actin layer line, ALL.
Jiangkun Wei: So, for example, myosin hat are arranged in vertebrate muscle. Myosin hat are arranged in levels or crowns. This is crown, the myosin head crowns. They are separated by approximately 14.3 nanometers.
Jiangkun Wei: And… this axial repeat produces strong M3 reflections. This is the reflection Coming from this one.
Jiangkun Wei: And, also the M6 and M15, they are the higher order reflections corresponding to… to these structures.
Jiangkun Wei: The feature away from the meridiano line is, are the layer lines.
Jiangkun Wei: This arise because actin and myosin are helical organized, rather than, like, a straight broad.
Jiangkun Wei: So the myosin hat produce myosin layer lines, again, and the acting produce acting layer lines
Jiangkun Wei: I'll take an acting example.
Jiangkun Wei: So, actin is commonly described as a 13 over 6 helix. So, there are approximately 13 actin monomers, a range over 6
Jiangkun Wei: 6 turns. So, if you count from here.
Jiangkun Wei: 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8, 9, 10.
Jiangkun Wei: 11, 12, 13, and this is one pitch. And… yeah, there are 6 turns here.
Jiangkun Wei: So… Best repeat.
Jiangkun Wei: has a spacing of 80… 38.7 nanometers, and this repeat corresponds to the… Let me see…
Jiangkun Wei: Oh, it doesn't show here. So this repeat actually…
Jiangkun Wei: Correspond to the reflection around here.
Jiangkun Wei: So there is a 30.8 nanometer reflection, it's not shown here. But if you look at the left-hand helix pitch.
Jiangkun Wei: Between two monomers.
Jiangkun Wei: The pitch is 5.9 nanometer, and it correspond to the… this actin layer line 6, this reflection.
Jiangkun Wei: And if you use the right-hand helix to see the pitch is 5.1 nanometer, it corresponds to actin layer 7. And sometimes when you stretch the muscle, you can see their… because the actin is kind of being stretched, their spacing will…
Jiangkun Wei: In real space, their spacing would increase, so the space between
Jiangkun Wei: Acting layer line 7 will decrease a bit in the diffraction patterns.
Jiangkun Wei: Okay, now I will give the time to Casey to give you an example of the meridian Arnold reflections.
Casey King: Absolutely. So, yeah, Jiangkun, I think, since we already got a good example, and we've talked a lot about all of the technical things, we actually have a couple examples here for you guys, but we only have about 10 minutes left, and we want to leave a little bit of time for questions, so I think we should just skip to the analysis portion and the muscle X at the end. What do you think, Jiangkun?
Jiangkun Wei: Do we skip this example?
Casey King: Yeah, yeah, I think we
Casey King: example, and we just go to the technical side. I'll go ahead and try and share my screen. We had another little bit of discussion about argon here, so just a couple interesting facts. So this is the advanced photon source. Simon already talked about this, but to give you a sense of scale, it's like a quarter of a mile in diameter.
Casey King: So it's really big, and they really, like.
Casey King: they need to make it, this big, because they're accelerating the electrons and the particles in the beam near the speed of light. So… and… and that's exactly how they generate such high intensity photons. So it's just… it's really cool to talk about the facility, and so go to the next one as well, Jiangkun. So yeah, let's talk about this a little bit, too. So, you know, we don't just…
Casey King: take the beam from the entire synchrotron and put it straight onto the sample, that would definitely cook the sample. That'd be way too much radiation, it would…
Casey King: fry your muscle, your muscle would die immediately. So actually, we take the beam, which is basically from the undulator on the right side of the image, Jiangkun, you can, yeah, great. Yeah, we're looking at the schematic over on the right.
Casey King: And you can pass the beam through this silicon crystal. So that, actually, silicon 111, that's a Miller indices, but it's a three-dimensional lattice, not a two-dimensional lattice like muscle. So you have this silicon-111 monochrometer. So mono meaning one, chrome meaning color, so you're isolating one wavelength
Casey King: And then, basically, there's a bunch of mirrors and stuff that pass
Casey King: the beam through the sample all the way to the detector, which you see as the CCD at the end. So, Jiangkun, go ahead, go next. So this is… once you get to the point of the detector, so this is an example of a mouse soleus muscle that was actually placed in the beam.
Casey King: By one of our collaborators, Wei collaborators, Wei Kong Ma, and he, he designs great experiments to, to…
Casey King: test muscle using this X-ray diffraction technique. So now we're going to show you what it's like when we have an image. So I'm going to go ahead and share my screen real quick. That's… that's what a unfiltered image looks like. So now let me go ahead and share here.
Casey King: Perfect. Can everyone see my screen?
Casey King: Okay, great. So this is an unedited image. Because we pass… because in our experiments, so this is a, I can actually tell you by looking at it.
Casey King: I'm gonna change the intensity real quick, so we can… we can change the intensity like this. I actually made it a little too bright. Let's make it a little less bright.
Casey King: We want to look at these, these, peaks right here. So this is the 1-O, as we've talked about, the 11 and the 2-0. So we know that this is insect flight muscle, because the 2O is so bright relative to the 1-1.
Casey King: So, what do you do with an image once you get this kind of raw image, and there's detector gaps here? The gaps are there so that the… if the beam is too bright and it breaks one of the panels, you don't have to replace all of the panels. And so, yeah, we have this detector, and we have this image, so what do you do after this? Well.
Casey King: let me go ahead and change. So this is just the X-ray viewer. I can just kind of view intensities here.
Casey King: And I can, change the intensity of the image. If I want to see meridionals, I can make it very bright, and we can zoom out, we can see great stuff on the meridional axis. So, let me go ahead and stop sharing this real quick.
Casey King: And show you what it's like to analyze a, the equatorial peaks using this software.
Casey King: And we can do that real quick and see if you guys have any questions. I know we have about 5 minutes left here, so let's see. Desktop… okay…
Casey King: Great.
Casey King: So now, I'm gonna share this screen.
Casey King: So now we have, the software that was designed by the BioCAD team at Argonne to specifically point out,
Casey King: equatorial peaks. So, there's a little bit of bias towards vertebrate biology, by the folks at Argon here, because when you first look at this X-ray diffraction image.
Casey King: it picked up two of the peaks, so the analysis worked great. It automatically did it for me. It found the intensity peaks based on the intensity of the light and the intensity of the pixel brightness.
Casey King: And it found the 1O and the 11 peaks, but we're studying insect flight muscles, so we need that 2-0 peak. The 2-0 peak gives us an indication
Casey King: as to how many of the myosin heads are binding. So the brighter this 2O peak is, the more myosin heads that have bound to actin.
Casey King: So, interestingly here, the 2O is actually much brighter than the 1O, and this is what you would expect for an image like this, because the muscle is actually under tetanus for this specific specimen. So, I can show you a little bit of what goes on here. We have
Casey King: Basically, this is just an intensity over 2D space of the pixels here. So, intensity is this way, and then it's measuring the pixels in just one axis, essentially. And we have…
Casey King: the 1-0, which is actually the brightest, then the 1-1, and then we have the 2-0. So, if we wanted to measure that one, we just do this manual peak selection, and we go through, and sometimes this takes two tries, but
Casey King: It's, the software's pretty good, so we just select all our peaks, and then we say done. It didn't work first time. I don't know why that happens.
Casey King: there's bugs in all software, but what's great is we know the developers of this software, so we can always reach out to them directly to get things fixed. But great! Now I have all my peaks there, and because I already calibrated my image, I can see, for example, a D10 spacing. This is very similar to the value that John Kuhn calculated earlier, it's very near 45 nanometers. So what happens after you've done that for
Casey King: hundreds of images. Well, now you can transition to…
Casey King: this spreadsheet where all that data populates, and I can just share this real quick here.
Casey King: And… yeah, the software is very intuitive, and it's… it's… But…
Casey King: the calibration is probably the most important part, which I didn't get to show you, but basically all the data populates into this Excel file, and we can go and see, oh, here's the D10, what happens to the lattice spacing over the course of tetanus? So we can just look at a graph real quick here.
Casey King: And we see, okay, over the course of tetanus, the lattice spacing is decreasing. But that's what you would expect, right? Because as the muscle contracts more, and more myosin heads bind, you are bringing that lattice spacing closer in
Casey King: Over time, and so, yes, you would expect the D10 spacing to shorten. So, that was a little crash course, very fast crash course on muscle X. So, there you have it.
Casey King: Does anybody have any questions about X-ray diffraction? We have 2 minutes.
Casey King: Maybe there's one question in there,
Casey King: Somewhere out there, you have to be confused about something, because…
Casey King: I'm still confused about a lot of things with X-ray diffraction.
Jiangkun Wei: Thank you, Casey.
Casey King: Yes, of course.
Chastain, Maddy: I have a question.
Chastain, Maddy: I was wondering what the restrictions are of, like, the living muscles you… or living muscles you can use, and, like, muscle types, and…
Chastain, Maddy: those type of restrictions for X-ray diffraction.
Casey King: Sure, so I think as long as you have, like, the typical muscle physiology restrictions, like, as long as you're following those, there's not, you know…
Casey King: For the most part, if you're passing a specimen through the beam, you're not intending to preserve that animal. It's going to be exposed to a lot of radiation.
Casey King: It doesn't quite kill the muscle tissue super fast, so you can do experiments for a couple hours. So, yeah, you just…
Casey King: There, there are… there are regulations, but, yeah, most… for the most part, we're using, like, ex vivo, the muscle gets dissected out of the body of whatever animal we're doing our experiments on.
Casey King: Okay, we have another question, and did that answer your question?
Casey King: Okay, we have another question in the chat. Confused, of course, this is tough. Curious, most common muscle samples you look at. So, okay,
Casey King: the…
Casey King: Probably the most interesting muscle sample that's been used in the history of X-ray diffraction is the Lothoceros beetle.
Casey King: It's a giant water beetle, and its flight muscle is one of the most crystalline of any insect or animal that has ever been measured or seen in X-ray diffraction. And we think that the highly crystalline structure contributes to just power production, so the more crystalline the structure, the more regular the myosin heads can bind, and the better force production and power production that that animal can have to fly.
Casey King: So Lothosterous beetles, which are just giant water beetles, are common. And then,
Casey King: Some of our collaborators, they use mouse soleus muscle, so,
Casey King: Why mouse soleus muscle? I… I don't actually… I don't actually think I know the answer to that. Go ahead, Jiangkun.
Jiangkun Wei: I think the striated muscles are with better periodic structure, so you can actually shoot the X-ray beam to all the muscle kinds, but the striated muscle is more regular, so you can see more
Jiangkun Wei: Because the X-ray diffraction comes from the periodic structure.
Jiangkun Wei: Right, so if the muscle is more…
Jiangkun Wei: Arranged in a more periodically way, so you can have better information, more information.
Casey King: Exactly, exactly.
Jiangkun Wei: Exactly.
Casey King: Any other questions? Those are great questions.
Casey King: Looks like we're one minute over,
Casey King: Don't want to keep too much of anyone else's time, especially if there are no more questions.
Jiangkun Wei: Yeah.
Jiangkun Wei: Vieira.
Casey King: I love you.
Jiangkun Wei: You guys still emailed us.
Casey King: Yes, of course. Always reach out.
Victoria Wood: Awesome. Thanks, guys, so much. This is such complex material, and this was a great explanation of it. I will… oh, yeah, we… no questions. I'll definitely post this, like I had the others, and I… I recommend,
Victoria Wood: Watching the recording, if you want to go back and, and,
Victoria Wood: Go over some of that material. And then, yes, let me post the barcode real quick.
Victoria Wood: Or the… the link for the sign-in.
Victoria Wood: There's the sign-in link, so yeah, make sure you, sign in.
Victoria Wood: And, yeah, if you forgot to sign in at a previous workshop, you can always, sign in after the fact. It just has that same… you can submit multiple times, and just…
Victoria Wood: Complete the reflection question there for the previous workshop.
Victoria Wood: In a separate submission.
Casey King: Alright, thank you so much, Victoria.
Victoria Wood: Thank you.
Casey King: Everyone.
Jiangkun Wei: Thank you.